Okay, let's get started. So, uh, in this
session, um, we're pleased to introduce
Nathan Harvey. Uh, Nathan is the Dora
lead and developer advocate at Google's,
uh, cloud Dora team. If you've not heard
of, I'm sure I'm sure Nathan's going to
go into a lot of this. Um, but if you
not heard of Dora, they've they've
actually just released a report. They do
a huge amount of super interesting uh
reports and data and stats on a whole
bunch of things. Uh this more recent one
is all about AI uh adoption and and how
AI dev tools are used, AI coding tools
are used. Um yeah, there's a 2025 report
that was just released which uh which
Nathan's going to talk through and uh
yeah, really excited to hear some of the
stats in this. So without further ado,
please welcome Nathan on stage.
>> All right. Hey, thanks so much. [music]
[applause]
All right, thank you so much and good
morning everyone. Uh, as was mentioned,
my name is Nathan Harvey. I lead up the
DORA program for Google Cloud. How many
of you have heard of Google Cloud? All
right. All right. That's good. That's
good. Uh, you know, DOR is all about
research and so I'm always running
surveys. So, thank you for raising your
hand for me. That gives me good data to
take back with me. I can go back and
tell my boss everyone has heard about
Google Cloud. Um, what you might not
have heard about, this just happened
yesterday. Gemini 3 was launched. Who's
had a chance to play with that? All
right, that's awesome. And another part,
another thing that was launched
yesterday. I don't know if you've even
heard of this. Anti-gravity. Who's heard
of anti-gravity? Oh, great. All the same
people, man. This is awesome. We're like
at 100% uh saturation. Everyone is aware
of it. If you haven't, the few of you
that didn't raise your hand, maybe you
just don't like raising your hand.
That's cool. Uh, anti-gravity is the
Aentic IDE that Google launched just
yesterday. So, go check it out. Have fun
with it. Of course, it's free to
download and use and you get access to
Gemini 3 and a bunch of other models
with that. But while I am a Google
Google employee, I'm not here to talk
about Google Google specific stuff
today. I'm here to talk about this
program called Dora. And as was
mentioned, Dora is a research program.
This research program looks into the
capabilities and conditions that enable
high-erforming technologydriven teams to
thrive. The beauty, one of the beauties
of this research program is that it's
been running for well over a decade now.
So, we have a lot of data and a lot of
history to really understand what does
it take to create this high performing
team and high performing organizations.
And Dora, if you've if you've followed
Dora for a while, you may know Dora by
its acronym, but I want to just let you
know that Dora has deacron. So if
someone asks you what does DORA stand
for, you can proudly say DORA stands for
nothing. Uh but that doesn't really
sound right. So we have this new tagline
that uh I would allow you to say Dora is
about how do we help teams get better at
getting better. The reality is that this
space is moving so fast. technology has
always done so and it's really important
for us as teams and organizations to be
on a journey and a mindset and even a
practice of continuous improvement and
continuous learning. And so I think
that's really uh summed up in that
message there. Now Dora every year runs
a global survey. We go out into the
world and we ask lots and lots of
questions of as many people as we can.
So while Dora does live within Google
Cloud, this is not research about Google
Cloud. This is research that is program
and platform agnostic to really
understand how you're doing things
today. In 2025, we had the pleasure of
hearing survey responses from nearly
5,000 people. We augment those survey
responses with qualitative interviews.
So, we have over a 100 hours of
qualitative data as well. Now, uh, you
can download our latest report here, and
you can see that on the screen here.
And, and just as a favor to every
presenter that you're going to see
across the next day, if you see a QR
code on the screen, please lift up your
phone. I don't care what you do with
your phone, just lift it up. It It helps
the speakers feel like I'm connecting
with the audience. Look, I put a QR code
up and they lifted up their phone. Take
a selfie for all I care. I can't see
what you're doing on the phone. It just
makes me feel good. Now, I would give
you time to read the report before I
continue the talk, but in honesty, it's
142page report, so ain't nobody got time
for that. I highly suggest you take this
report and give it to Notebook LM and
say, "Hey, summarize this report for
me." And then you could figure out which
parts of it you really want to dig into.
But before we uh go much deeper, I want
to kind of share the overall finding of
this report. Like if I were to summarize
it in three slides, I just said if I'm
about to summarize it in three slides.
AI's primary role in software
development is that of an amplifier.
The greatest returns on AI investment
come from a strategic focus on the
underlying organizational system.
Without this focus, without this
foundation, AI creates localized pockets
of productivity that are often lost to
downstream chaos. And maybe you've felt
this, maybe you've even seen it. There
are vendors out there with these AI
tools that say AI is going to help you
be 30% faster
at what? 30% faster writing a function.
yeah. Uh, does that matter? I mean,
yeah, of course it matters, but is does
it matter to the overall system? Does it
matter to your customers that you were
able to write that function 30% faster?
Maybe, maybe not. So, I I want to before
we go any further, and this is going to
be another moment for you, although this
one's going to be a little bit more
participatory, I want to ask you a
question
right now. What's stopping you from
yoloing that code that AI wrote into
production?
What's stopping you? Don't no, don't
shout out the answer. I mean, nothing is
a good answer, but if you go to this QR
code or this menty and enter in the
code, it's going to ask you that
question. I'd love you to just type in
an answer. What's stopping you from just
it, ship it. I shouldn't curse so
early in the morning, but here we are.
I am in Brooklyn, so maybe it's okay.
All right. Uh, we're going to take it
just a quick glance over here and see
how are folks answering. Aha. All right.
Good stuff. Good stuff. We've got a
couple of answers so far. And like we
can come back and check this throughout
the day or throughout the next couple of
days. Uh, nothing is great. Like
awesome. The AI wrote it. Ship it to
production. Let's see what happens. I
love that. Security vulnerabilities, uh,
customers, it yelled at me, customer
risk, lots of different reasons why. And
I would just I would just encourage you
to actually think about this seriously
with your team. And every answer that
you come up with, this is maybe a good
thing for you to focus on. Why can't you
just ship that code into production?
Maybe we didn't give it enough context.
Maybe we need to talk to the folks at
Tessle and say, "Hey, how do we generate
better code with AI?" Let's do so and
address some of these concerns that you
see here. Security, fear, fear.
I I like how it's uh fear nothing uh is
kind of how it's arranged here. Yes, you
should definitely fear nothing. All
right. Uh let's get back to not my
email. You didn't want to see that. Oh,
you don't want to see that either. Let's
see. Where am I?
There we go.
I can sometimes
navigate slides. All right. So what did
we find in the report? I want to share
some information about AI adoption and
usage. Now before I share this next
slide, uh I I want to see how much you
were paying attention. How do we collect
most of our data?
>> Surveys.
Surveys, right? It would be awesome if
all of you would give us all of your
telemetry so that we could analyze that,
but you don't. Uh and actually, thank
you. Surveys are good enough for me. But
there is a little challenge. I know
you're sitting there thinking, "Surveys,
man, come on, right?" Well, let's look
at AI adoption and usage. What this
slide shows us is that 10% of the people
that take our survey lie.
Oh, no. That's not what this shows. This
this answers the question, are you using
AI at work? 90% of the people said yes.
10% said no. So, uh I I think it's kind
of safe to say that AI adoption is
pretty much universal. We could have
asked, "Are you using a computer at
work?" And we might have seen similar
responses this year. So I don't think
we'll ask this question next year. But
we want to ask and understand more than
just adoption. What about your reliance?
Are you relying on work uh on AI at
work? So 95% of those survey respondents
that say they're using AI are relying on
it for at least something that they're
doing at work. And of course, our survey
talks to more than just software
developers. So this doesn't necessarily
mean that you're relying on it for code,
but maybe you're a product manager.
Maybe you're relying on it to help you
write specs or to help you write design
documents or what have you. And then we
have this other question. All right,
you're relying on it. How much are you
using it? Is Steve Yagi here yet? You
could see that Steve Yagi took our our
uh survey this year. How many hours in a
recent working day did you spend working
with AI? 12 hours. That is the Steve
Yagi factor right there. I know Jean,
you're here. Steve works 12 hours a day
interacting with AI. If if if you find
that you're one of these people over
here, stop. Please stop. Take a break.
996 is a thing, but like you should take
a break. Take a break. Step away from
the AI. But [gasps] the interesting
thing here is the median time spent is 2
hours a day. Two hours a day. And what I
find really fascinating about this is
there there have been plenty of studies
that say, how much time does a software
engineer spend actually writing code?
And when we do those studies, the range
is like 11 to 32%.
That's how much time you actually spend
writing code as a software engineer. Uh
30% is about 2 hours a day. Like they're
pretty close to one another. So you're
probably using AI when you're writing
code. Is it helping you? Do you feel
more productive? And of course, there's
the meter study that was brought up
earlier. find me at a break and we'll we
can talk about how I like my take on
that meter study. But what we see here
is over a good a huge proportion of our
survey respondents say yes I feel more
productive when I'm using AI. Uh not
only that it's improving the underlying
quality of the codebase that I'm working
with. So you're using AI interacting
with a codebase. Is that code getting
better or worse? Most say it's getting
better. Some say h it's not really
having an impact. But only uh about 10%
say it's actually getting worse. And you
know, many people will say, well, if
it's making your codebase worse, you're
probably not doing it right. Right. So
just AI harder and things will get
better. All right. This is interesting
though because we have a lot of
reliance. I feel like it's helping me
and it's improving the underlying
quality of my code. But how much do you
trust the output of AI? Well, we find
that about 30% of our survey respondents
trust the output of AI a little or not
at all. I don't trust it. Uh, you know,
that little or not at all, I don't know.
I I'm I'm like I'm team somewhat
46%. I somewhat trust it. I want to sit
down and have a coffee with 7% of the
people from our survey though. Those
that trust it a great deal. Can we have
a conversation? And those that trust it
not at all. like this 11% I want to get
you in a room and talk about this
because I think you're both wrong. I
think team somewhat is the right answer.
We have to trust but verify anything
that's generated by AI. And this could
be code. It could be the email you're
about to send off to your manager. It
could be the performance review you're
writing for your direct report. Like
please don't just ship it. Don't just
yolo it for all the reasons that we saw
earlier that you shared. Another thing
that's interesting that we talked about
and it it feels really weird in this
audience. I just want to remind all of
you we are living in the future. We are
ahead of so many different people out
there in the industry. That's the truth.
What we asked also about is your
frequency of AI interaction. What mode
are you interacting with AI? And
interestingly, 61% of our survey
respondents said they had never
interacted in an agentic mode.
Now, I should point out and I do point
out just to be very clear, do you see
that little tiny text down there at the
bottom? Our survey was fielded mid June
to mid July of 2025.
So, in that time, only about 40% of our
respondents had ever interacted with an
agent. Today, I think that number would
be like there'd be more people that have
interacted. But I still think it's it's
fair to point out that as individuals
and more so as teams and more so as
organizations, we only have so much
capacity for change. And so while
Agentic AI is all the hotness on social
media, the reality is you might not be
using it on your team yet. And so don't
feel bad. It's okay. And if you are,
just remember you're living in the
future. You are ahead of most of the
people that are in our industry
together.
But Dora like we want to understand more
than just if or how you're using thing.
We want to understand what is the impact
of that. So one of the things that we're
able to do is we create this model that
shows the answers to all of the
questions that we have. We basically
give you a score across a bunch of
different capabilities and outcomes. And
we're able to give you a score as an
example for AI adoption. What does it
mean to have a score of seven for AI
adoption? I don't know. It doesn't
really mean anything. It's just a
number. But when we think about this, AI
adoption has a couple of different
factors that go into this. Your reliance
on AI, how much do you trust it? And how
much are you reflexively using it? Now,
because we can sort of model that in our
survey responses, we can create a model
of everything that we're asking about
and we can run some simulations. So,
let's say your AI adoption score was
seven. What if we cranked it up to nine?
What would the impact be? We can run a
bunch of simulations across our data to
understand what that probable impact
might be. Now, the reality is you can't
do this on your team. I was talking to
someone at at coffee this morning.
They're like, "So, how do we test this?
Like, do we tell team A you can use AI
and team B like no AI for you and then
we just see what the results are?" Like,
you shouldn't do that within your
organization and it's not going to give
you a lot of great valid responses or
data. So, you should take what we find
as kind of predictions. So what we do we
say what if we amp up this AI adoption
factor and how is it going to impact
things downstream. So if it impacts the
things downstream, not at all. It falls
right on this dash line here. And what
are those things downstream? These sort
of outcomes that we talk about
individual effectiveness to the right of
that dash line, it's going up. So that's
good. We see individual effectiveness
goes up quite significantly. Software
delivery instability
also goes up,
which is not really what we want, but it
nevertheless, it's what happens. And the
way we measure, so I'll talk about that
later. uh organizational performance,
val time doing valuable work, code
quality, product performance, software
delivery throughput, all of these things
increase. So that's all very positive.
And then our last two outcomes are
burnout and friction. What happens to
those when you use more AI? Actually,
not much. Statistically, those are both
basically zero. And I think that makes a
ton of sense. If you're feeling burnt
out at work, you know, you're cynical
about work, you can't separate work life
from home life and someone comes to you
and says, "Well, here's a new tool
that'll fix your burnout." It's not
going to fix your burnout. We all know
that, right? So, the nice thing though
is burnout isn't really increasing
because maybe a new tool could increase
your burnout. So, largely this is a
positive signal here. using more AI can
have some real good benefits, but we
want to dig even deeper than that and
understand like how are various teams
performing. And so one way that Dora has
looked at team performance for many many
years, we sort of have this center of
gravity around software delivery
performance. One more question for you.
How many of you have heard of Dora's
software delivery performance metrics or
the Dora metrics, the four keys? Yeah,
awesome. All right, so Dora has these
four keys for software delivery
performance. Um, and you'll see on this
slide that I'm very bad at math. Okay,
there are five, not four, uh, five keys
now for the last two years. But with the
way we measure software delivery
performance, we look at throughput and
we look at stability. And what we've
found interestingly across the years is
that throughput and stability are not
trade-offs of one another. You are
either fast and stable or you are slow
and unstable. So as Dave Farlay once
said, you have a choice. You can either
have better software faster or you can
have slower soft or worse software
slower. [snorts] Your choice. Better
faster software or worse software
slower. You decide. You probably want
that better software faster. But you
know looking at this doesn't really give
us a full picture of how is a team
doing. And also if you add agents to the
mix, do you need different metrics?
Probably not. These still tell you how
software delivery performance is going.
But we want to look deeper. So this year
we did an analysis across all of these
teams, across other factors, factors
like team performance, product
performance, uh individual
effectiveness, how much time do you
spend doing valuable work, and so forth.
And what we found when we looked across
our sample set of 5,000 was kind of
seven different team types emerged. So,
we gave all of these team types names.
Everything from like foundational
challenges or legacy bottleneck through
to those harmonious high achievers. Some
teams are performing really well across
all of those characteristics and some
not so much. What does that look like?
This is a great time to take a picture
if you like. Here's what it looks like.
I'll just let you read this chart really
quickly. I'll stand here silently while
you do so.
Okay? You can't actually read that
chart. There's too much information on
this slide. It's hard to read and we do
some really weird things with radar
charts. So, this is just another reason
to go download the report and read it.
But the key point here is we see nearly
universal AI adoption yet a high level
of variability in team performance. So,
what's going on? This tells us that it
it can't be AI adoption that drives all
of this because if it were, we'd see a
lot more similarity across these teams.
So we asked this question as part of our
research and what we came up with is
what we call the Dora AI capabilities
model. What capabilities and conditions
do you need to have as a team and an
organization in place to make sure that
AI adoption actually amplifies those
outcomes that you care about? Things
like team performance and product
performance. And what we were able to
assess through our analysis is that the
teams that are doing well with AI
adoption tend to have these seven
capabilities or conditions in place. And
it starts with a clear and communicated
stance on how we should use AI within
our organization. If you don't know what
the rules are around using AI in your
organization, it's likely to introduce
friction and burnout and slow you down
and it's just not good. So start with a
clear and communicated stance. But we
also have to have things like healthy
data ecosystems and giving AI access to
our data. A guy talked about context
engineering like this is context
engineering. How does the AI know about
your internal policies? How does it know
about your practices and your team norms
and so forth. But it's also things that
we've studied for a long long time. You
have to have strong version control
practices. You should be checking in
code very very frequently as the AI is
writing it. This not only helps you uh
sort of understand what the AI is doing
but it also gives you that safety net to
roll back to a previous good state as
required. Working in small batches was
always a big thing to help us drive
software delivery performance. It turns
out that like as humans we're better at
solving a small problem.
Guess who else is better at solving a
small problem? AI agents. Like if you
give them a smaller problem to solve,
they will do better at it than if you
give them a giant problem to solve.
Today that's true. Like in the future,
does that change? I don't know. But
let's go figure that out together. Also
having a userentric focus and a quality
internal platforms are super important.
The way that this model sort of
manifests, it looks like this. On the
left hand side, we have those outcomes
that you care about. We know that you're
adopting AI. So how do you make sure
that AI has the biggest impact on those
outcomes? You have these capabilities
and conditions in place. So how might
you use this model within your team?
Well, let's say oh sorry I know none of
you are part of the legacy bottleneck
team. If you were, you'd be back at work
trying to uncover like why is everything
broken right now? You're not in that
state, but let's say you were just for a
moment. One of the things that we see
about the legacy bottleneck team is that
their product performance is really low.
So maybe they decide as a team, we want
to improve our product performance and
we know we're going to use AI because
well we've been mandated to use AI and
it's fun. So let's use more AI. You can
use the door AI capabilities model to
say product performance is that outcome
that we want to improve. We know that AI
adoption has a relationship with product
performance, but we want to amplify that
impact. Follow the arrows backwards from
product performance and you find these
are the three capabilities that as a
team we should focus on. So now if I
want to make sure that my agents are
doing the best job that they can or the
AI assistance that I'm getting is the
best possible, I want to make sure that
I have good access to internal data,
that I'm working in small batches, and I
have that clear and communicated stance.
So regardless of where you are as a
team, this model can help you get the
most out of AI. And I want to try to
save a little bit of time for questions.
I might have time for one. So I want to
jump to some final thoughts. First
remember the way we get our research. We
go out and we research the world and
then we report our findings. I'm sorry
to tell you none of you work for the
world. You work in an organization and
within that organization you work on
some specific applications or services
and so forth. So it is really important
that you take our findings and
contextualize them for your team. I
often say that you should take our
findings and use them as the hypothesis
for the next experiment you're going to
run as the team. Like don't take us at
our our results at at face value. You've
got to put them into practice. And then
finally, I think it's really important
and congratulations. You're here today
as part of a community. You can't do
this alone. We're all learning together.
And so if you're part of the AI native
dev community, great. Continue to be
there. Also, this is a test. What did I
tell you at the beginning? There's a QR
code on this slide. I see very few
people holding up their phones. I'm very
very disappointed. Um, so the Dora
community is where we have thousands of
leaders and practitioners and
researchers just like you where we come
together and share information about how
we're taking these ideas and putting
them into practice. One more time for
those phones. I mean, one more time for
you to download the report. Uh, the
report goes into much more detail than I
have time for today. Although I am
around all day. So if you have
additional questions, want to talk more
about methodology, any of it, I'm happy
to have that uh conversation. And with
that, we might have time for one sec
question, I'm not sure. You tell me.
>> Yeah, we can grab a question. Any
question have one online as well. Take
one here and then a very quick actually
the quick one online while I'm walking.
Ops excellence uh used to be a metric, a
dorometric a while ago. Why was it
pulled? If you could answer that one
quickly.
>> Yep, I sure can. Operational excellence
used to be a Dora metric. Why was it
pulled? Uh the reality is that we still
care about operational performance but
operational performance we inaccurately
in the past called it the fifth metric.
Operational performance and software
delivery performance are two different
but very related things. So we haven't
removed it. We just we just talk about
it in a more clear way today and then
question from the back.
>> Great presentation. Thank you. So we all
of the stuff that you said makes sense.
as we try and move forward, we'll kind
of have like different initiatives that
we'll go after. And when we try and
measure the impact of those,
>> yes,
>> it's very difficult to separate the kind
of correlation with causality. And even
the most senior management folks
typically don't understand the the
difference between the two.
>> So what inevitably happens is you go,
"Oh, because you're using XI AI, we're
x% more efficient." even though we're x%
more efficient because it's summer and
that's when we churn out all of our
stuff.
>> Yes.
>> How how do you approach solving that
challenge?
>> Yeah. So, one of the ways that I
approach solving that challenge is uh
advice that is maybe not going to help
you at all. It is really important to
have a baseline. So, if if uh and I talk
to so many people today who are like is
AI going to help me improve productivity
by 30%. I say well how are you measuring
productivity today? and their answer is
blink blink blink well then yes it'll
help you by 30%. We can set whatever
measures we want and prove that those
have improved by 30%. I think your point
though is well taken that you you can't
change just one thing about your
organization. So we have if we can look
at trends and we can see oh last summer
our productivity went up this summer our
productivity went up the delta between
the two is we're using a lot more AI is
did it go up at a different rate this
year maybe it didn't go up quite as much
you have to have that comprehensive view
and then when it comes to the measures
that you put in place I think it's
always important to remember two things
what is the question we're trying to
answer and what behavior changes are we
going to put in place when that measure
doubles or when that measure gets cut in
half. If you can start having those
conversations, at the end of the day,
the only reason to have a metric is to
start a conversation. And the reason you
have that conversation is to change how
you're working. So, take that uh as as
an answer. I got a thumbs up. And I'm
out of time.
>> That's all good. Thank you very much.
And please uh please give it up for
Nathan.
>> Thank you very [music] much.
Heat. Heat.
[music]
>> [music]